





Technical Specialist, Researcher

WHO AM I?

I would consider myself a technophile and have been known to not give up on things that tickle the brain. My goal is to keep contributing to the technologically rich society that we are in today. With my experience and education, I have been exposed to CAD and FEM simulations, numerics, programming, HPC, real-time systems and a bit of ML/AI.

















CAD



Git



LaTeX

EDUCATION

2018 – 2020 Master's Degree – Computational and Data Science

Indian Institute of Science (IISc), Bangalore, India

GPA - 8.20/10

2014 - 2018 Bachelor's Degree - Mechanical Engineering

SSN College of Engineering - Anna University, Chennai, India

GPA - 8.36/10

2012 – 2014 **High School**

Passed with overall 94%

SBIOA Model Matric Higher Secondary, Chennai, India

EXPERIENCE

2020 - Present

Technical Specialist

Bosch India - Research and Technology Centre

Worked with an international team of researchers, solving problems related to numerical methods and solutions of ODEs in single precision embedded hardware for real-time systems, worked on the implementation of ODE solvers, Kalman filters, online optimizers and related algorithms, parameter tuning in ODE systems and also exposed to hybrid modelling methods such as PINNs, Neural ODEs, etc.

C / Python / Matlab / Julia / Git

2018 - 2020

Graduate Research Assistant

Indian Institute of Science (IISc)

Worked on building a patient-specific computational model of the human cornea and estimating parameters with experimental data with which the modelled patient-specific cornea behavior can be determined and can relate to some illness

C/C++ / Python / FEM tools / Linux

May to July 2019

Data Science Intern

Reliance Industries Limited

Worked with a team of experts on machine learning and performed sentence classification with state-of-the-art algorithms and also built a dashboard for hosting and data collection

Python

March 2018 **Design Validation Intern**

Valkan Engineering

Worked with structural designs relating to the placement of solar panels and analyzed the same by applying wind loads from CFD simulations

CAD / Ansys

December 2016

Project Intern

Steinbeis Solar Research Center

Worked on developing a CAD model of an underwater remote-operated vehicle for prototyping

CAD / Ansys

ACADEMIC PROJECTS

Quantification of Biomechanical Properties of Human Cornea with Finite Element Method

Master's Dissertation

Patient-specific finite element model of the cornea was built with open source FEM tools using Zernike polynomials fitted to the cornea, material parameters of the finite element model were recovered from measurement data (synthetic), the goal is to use measurements from air puff test to identify material behavior of cornea and in turn, study the illness associated with patients

C/C++ / (2020)

Discontinuous Galerkin Method for 1D Advection

Course Project

Analyzed the use of discontinuous Galerkin method for the first order wave equation, created a 1D FEM library with linear and higher order elements, assembly and solver routines

C/C++ / (2019)

Finite Element Analysis of Tool Wear in Machining of Hastelloy

Bachelor's Project

Analysis of tool wear in the machining of Hastelloy material, microscopic images were taken and compared to finite element results, appropriate parameters were also tuned manually to get a better fit with the experiments

Deform 3D / (2018)

Numerical Study of Blade Profiles of Vertical Axis Wind Turbine with Bi-directional Wind Flow

Bachelor's CFD Project

CFD simulation of wind flow around a VAWT was performed and the starting of the turbine from rest was studied, assuming continuous bidirectional wind flow, the rpm progression with time until stabilization was also extracted

Ansys Fluent / (2017)

Cricket match simulation with decision tree classifier

Hobby Project

With the ball by ball dataset, a decision tree classifier model was built with certain features, and the model was used to create a simulation with a simple Tkinter interface where at each ball the model was used for predictions Python / (2018)

PUBLICATIONS AND PATENTS

Improving the Stability of Kalman Filters with Posit arithmetic

Ponsuganth Ilangovan P, Rohan Rayan, Vinay Shankar Saxena In progress – Conference on Next Generation Arithmetic (CoNGA) 2023

Numerical Study of Blade Profiles of Vertical Axis Wind Turbine (VAWT) with Bidirectional Wind Flow in Highway Roads

Arun Prakash, P. Ponsuganth Ilangovan, Nitin Joy, R. Subramanian – Advances in Energy Research, Vol. 2, Springer, https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-981-15-2662-6_33

Cutting forces and tool wear studies on machining of Hastelloy X

K.S. Vijay Sekar, K. Gobivel, G. Ram Goutham, P. Ponsuganth Elangovan, N. Naresh Babu – Materials Today: Proceedings, Volume 62, Part 2, 2022, Pages 852-857, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.matpr.2022.04.049

An Electronic Control Unit (ECU) for solving ordinary differential equations and a method thereof

Reference - IN202241037263A - To be updated in patbase

A Kalman Filtering Method and Filter Device

Reference - IN202041052051A

MOOC COURSES

Geometric Algorithms

Coursera - EIT Digital (2022)

Finite Element Method for Problems in Physics

Coursera - University of Michigan (2017)

Matlab Programming for Numerical computations

NPTEL - IIT Madras (2017)

HOBBY

Video editing, Cricket, Video games, Motorcycling, Hobby coding, Reading, Arduino and Raspberry pi, Creating Math videos